Hey there and welcome. This is the last in this four part series
on "Getting to grips with Monero".
In this video we're going to be exploring
ways in which you can easily enhance your
privacy as a Monero user.
We'll be exploring a few different networking
methods and account management practices.
Let's get into it.
To begin we want continue on from the last
video and introduce some
privacy enhancing account practices.
We're going to start by introducing a new
term: **ring signatures**.
Ring signatures are one of the key features
of the Monero ecosystem which aims to anonymise
our transactions.
To learn more have a look at the Moneropedia
entry.
Ring signatures aren't perfect as they only
provide plausible deniability.
Attacks can exist where two or more colluding
parties attempt to learn information about
someone they transact with.
They can do so by tracing transaction graphs
and performing statistical tests.
This type of attack is especially effective
against those who engage in repeated, uniform
transactions and also provide personally identifiable
information.
We won't be going into much detail so if you
want to learn more about the attacks available
to bad actors, please watch the breaking Monero
series.
A link to which will be in the description.
There are two simple things we can do to reduce
the risk imposed by these kinds of attacks.
The first is by reducing input mixing.
Input mixing is where you use owned outputs
with multiple origins to satisfy a new transaction.
Mixing inputs increases the amount of information
available to those who are interested and
can once again be used in a statistic analysis.
That moves us onto the second thing you can
do, churning.
Churning is the act of sending outputs to
yourself.
Churning increases the level of plausible
deniability as each of those outputs will
then be included in many more ring signatures
than before.
If you need to mix inputs the best thing to
do is churn them before mixing.
The "Coins" tab in Feather is great for managing
both of these practices.
To churn, simply right click on one of your
owned outputs and select "Sweep output".
When the new window opens, select "Send to
self (churn)".
**When using the send to self function, Feather
will send that output to your primary address.**
Another helpful feature of Feather wallet
is the ability to freeze outputs.
This is useful when you have multiple outputs
from different sources in the same account.
Freezing them prevents Feather from using
them when generating new transactions.
You'll notice that the available balance in
the tool bar has changed to reflect this.
With these ideas in mind in addition to what
was learnt in video three about account management,
you now have a wide range of tools to increase
your level of privacy when using the network.
So far, we have only shown you how to connect
to your own node from within your LAN.
But what if you want to spend Monero whilst
out shopping in town or when you're on holiday?
Generally speaking, connecting to different
nodes for one off payments is fine for maintaining
privacy, especially if you're using either
Feather or Monerujo which both support The
Onion Routing (Tor) Project.
However there have been several warnings throughout
this series, particularly with regards to
our network traffic.
During the second video we covered the kind
of information made available to both internet
service providers (ISPs) and node operators.
You should keep these things in mind when
making decisions about your networking preferences.
If your state has banned the use of Monero
or you don't trust your ISP, you may want
to manage this exposure and obfuscate your
interactions with the Monero blockchain.
Connecting to your own node through Tor or
a VPN is the best method for achieving this.
Although we are primarily focused on privacy,
there may be technical reasons for using a
VPN or Tor.
For example, your ISP may limit the use of
port forwarding or you may not be able to
access your router in an administrative capacity.
Before we continue, it would be good to introduce
two terms which you may not have come across before.
They are Clearnet and Darknet.
These terms have a well established history
and can be be simply summarised in the following ways:
Clearnet - Publicly accessible Internet, the one that you use day to day
Darknet - Internet that can only be accessed
with specific software, configurations, or authorisation,
For those of you who followed the previous
videos and were not able to host your own
node; you are already using the Darknet via
Tor.
Tor is a free and open-source software which
increases anonymity and censorship resistance
on the internet.
If you are interested in learning more please
visit the Tor project website.
In the next sections we'll be demonstrating
how to configure our nodes to accept RPC's
from outside our LAN.
Firstly using Clearnet and then Darknet, which
is aimed only at Linux users.
We have one more warning before diving in.
Opening ports comes with some risk, although
we didn't issue a warning for the P2P networking,
we will for RPC's.
The risk of opening ports is normally tightly
bound to the application that is being run
through that port.
Although there are no known vulnerabilities
in the RPC implementation, it doesn't mean
that there aren't any.
If you have concerns or problems with port
forwarding, we'd recommend you host your node
over Tor, which does not require you to do
this.
If you have no reason to obfuscate your interactions
with the Monero blockchain (and your router
supports it), all you need to do is add firewall
rules to your router and the machine which
hosts your node.
The default port for RPC's is **18081**.
If you haven't done so already, you should
add them now using the guide from the second
video; **Setting up your own node**.
You will then need to discover your external
IP address, which can most easily be done
by visiting 3rd party sites such as those
of VPN providers like Mullvad.
Once you have done this, you have all the
information you need to connect to your node.
Using a VPN is equivalent to changing your
ISP and depending on the service, you may
gain some privacy enhancing features.
In the last video we bought a subscription
to Mullvad, a privacy focused VPN provider
based in Sweden.
We specifically chose Mullvad because we are
able to configure multiple ports for use with
our daemons and we were able to maintain some
privacy when buying the subscription.
Let's get started by heading over to Mullvad's
web page and selecting "Get started".
Unlike services from Nord et al. which require
you to provide email addresses and other personally
identifying details, Mullvad uses account
numbers.
To generate an account number we can simply
click on the button provided.
Now that we have our number, it's time to
add some credit to our account.
As we already purchased some credit we can
select the **voucher** option and enter the
details there.
The final thing to do is download the appropriate
software for your OS and assign ports to your account.
Don't forget to verify your donwloads, Mullvads
public key along with their own guide can
be found through the following link or by
clicking "what is this?" on the downloads page.
As a VPN user the ports you have access to
will be limited.
The default ports for P2P connections (18080)
and RPC's (18081) will therefore likely be
unavailable.
To continue, we need to assign ports to our
account.
Once logged in, choose a location and then
a city using the drop down menu.
Now click on the settings icon and then select
"Advanced".
There are two types of tunnelling protocols
available through Mullvad, OpenVPN and WireGuard.
We suggest selecting WireGuard, but you are
free to make your own choice.
If you're interested in the differences, please
start with the links bellow.
Next, head back to Mullvads website and navigate
to your account page.
Once here, select "Manage ports and WireGuard
keys".
If you set your app to use WireGuard like
us, you'll see your key displayed here.
Scroll down to the "Port forwarding" subheading,
now select the city you chose within the app
and either the WireGuard key, or "No Key"
for those of you using OpenVPN.
Mullvad offers us the ability to forward up
to 5 ports.
Click on the green button to add ports, do
this at least twice.
As you can see a few items have appeared under
"ACTIVE PORTS".
Now that we have these ports it's time to
head back to our **bitmonero.conf** and change
the default ports.
The options are labelled `p2p-bind-port=`
and `rpc-bind-port=`, replace the numbers
which follow with the numbers given to you
by Mullvad.
Be sure to make a note of which ports you
add to each option.
You should then restart your daemon for these
settings to take effect.
Finally, you need to add rules in the firewalls
of both your computer and router.
Please follow the instructions from the second
video: **Setting up your own node**.
To connect to your node from outside your
LAN your wallet software will require the
port for RPC's and the IP address.
You should already know your port number;
to find our new IP address we can use the
drop down menu in the Mullvad app.
The IP address you need will be labeled "out".
Be warned, depending on your configuration,
these IP addresses may not be static and can
change without warning.
Be sure to check again if you are ever unable
to access your node.
In order to see how to add your node to Monerujo
or Feather, please move on the the section
called **Adding nodes to your wallet software**.
If you've had any problems with this process
please double check you have your port numbers
entered and forwarded correctly before reaching
out.
Now for the the Darknet approach.
Welcome to the dark side.
In this section, we'll be helping Linux users
set up a hidden service, aka an onion service.
Hidden services are a convenient method of
sharing local services on the internet.
This is achieved by routing the traffic through
tor and securing it with a private and complex
address, which can be further secured using
authorisation methods.
Although Tor is significantly slower than
the Clearnet alternative, it is much more private.
Onion addresses are not publicly available
and are extremely difficult to guess.
To continue with this part of the guide, you
need to have Tor installed on the machine
that hosts your node.
Installation depends on your distribution
and is not covered in this video.
If you need help, please consult the tor website.
After the installation process you should
now have a dedicated service which starts
with your machine each time.
To check if it's running use the command on screen.
Use `Ctrl + C` to exit.
With Tor installed it's rather simple to set
up a hidden service.
The first thing you need to do is edit the
Tor config file, which is typically located
in the following directory: `/etc/tor/torrc`.
If everything is well your status should show
that it's active and running.
Using your favourite editor you need to add
a few lines, which will define your new service.
I'm going to use vim
and to enter the editing window I will use
the command `sudo vim /etc/tor/torrc`, once
that's done I will add the following lines
Take note of the fact that the option **HiddenServicePort**
is a redirect of the already existing service
on your host PC.
If you have changed the default port for RPC's
then this line needs to change to reflect that.
You can also change the port on Tor to something
else as well.
We can now exit our editor, making sure to
save our changes.
For the changes to take effect we must restart
Tor, which should now be running as a service.
We can do this with the command that you see on screen
To ensure Tor has started correctly and the
settings have taken effect once again use
the command: `sudo systemctl status tor@default.service`.
Once again, use `Ctrl + C` to exit.
All that's left is to find out the hidden
service address which has been issued by Tor.
To print this information to the terminal
we can use the concatenate command, along
with the correct file location.
The full command should look like this: `sudo
cat /var/lib/tor/monero-service/hostname`.
We now have all the information we need to
connect to our node using Tor enabled wallets.
Now that we've done that let's take a look
at Monerujo.
Although at the time of making this video
Monerujo is currently an Android only wallet,
we're using it due to its simple Tor integration.
Please note, that for the Tor functionality
to be enabled you will also need to have Orbot installed.
In order to add your node to Monerujo, first
click on the network options.
Once on the node selection menu, you should
see a + symbol in the bottom corner.
Here we can enter our details.
In the "Hostname" field you should enter your
external IP address or onion address.
Once you've done that you need to enter the
port which has been assigned to RPCs.
You can name the node what ever you like and
for now we will leave the "Username" and "Password" fields blank.
With all of that information filled in we
can now select test to make sure everything
has been configured correctly.
If you have entered an onion address, this
process may not work initially.
Press ok to save your settings and then head
back to the main menu.
Click on the symbol next to the node name,
once that's initialised, you should now see
a little onion symbol, this means you are
now using Tor to route your traffic.
You can use Tor to connect to either Clearnet
or Darknet nodes, but bare in mind Tor is
much slower.
The process for adding your node to Feather
is fairly similar.
Start by selecting "File" and the "Settings".
Next, select the "Node" tab and then highlight
"From custom list".
You should then enter your IP or onion address
followed by the port number.
Click "OK" when you're done and then double
click on the node to connect to it.
There you have it, you are now able to use
your node from outside of your LAN.
You may have noticed that it's possible to
secure your RPC server with usernames and passwords.
With this in place only those with a given
username and password will be able to interact with the server.
To enable this, we need to head back to our
`bitmonero.conf` once more.
The flag for adding a username and password
pair is as follows: `rpc-login=username:password`.
This flag, along with many others can be found
via the Monerodocs website which you may remember
from the second video.
With that line added, you should now restart
your node for the settings to take effect.
Adding a username and password can grant you
a little peace of mind and helps to prevent
others from abusing your server.
In the last few videos we've covered a lot.
Don't worry if it all still seems a bit strange,
it will take some time and practice for this
information to be digested in it's entirety.
Please use these videos as a reference point
for any further learning.
The complete scripts for these videos are
hosted on the Monero Guides website and are
packed full of links to further reading which
we've referenced throughout these guides.
For additional reading, both Zero to Monero
and Mastering Monero offer a great level of
detail and are very valuable resources.
We want to close by thanking you for staying
tuned.
We hope you now have the tools to both start
and continue your journey with Monero.
So from us here at Monero Guides we wish you
the best of luck on your adventures and look
forward to seeing you again in future installments.
~moneroguides